stoicism is an ancient Greek scholar
force it was founded in Athens and 300
BCE and it was influenced by Socrates
and its central teaching is that virtue
is the only true goods and what that
really means is that what we do with our
character is the most important thing in
life it's much more important than
health wealth reputation or other things
that befall us because wealth is only
good if you use it wisely and virtuously
and the same with all these external
opportunities in life so Stoics think
the things that people chase after in
life are only really a value if you use
them wisely and therefore wisdom and
virtue of strength of character is the
most important thing in life and we
should all learn ways to focus on that
and cultivator stoicism means to me
taking control of your life or maybe
focusing on what's in control in your
life and acting accordingly what comes
to mind is genre Vicki's term of the
meaning crisis there's a sense that
there's a lack of meaning in our lives
and stoicism amongst all these other
different life stances and philosophies
like Buddhism
or existentialism is highly relevant to
the meaning crisis because if you adopt
the stoic standpoint then the idea is
you're living with purpose kind of like
a way to deal with what it is to be
human and to deal with like I guess the
chaos that is kind of life right now so
things get thrown at you all the time
there's adversity and almost life is a
bunch of kind of problems you could
almost say that we have to kind of solve
so I think stoicism is developing to me
is a way to look at situations that
arise in my life and how to respond to
them in a more skillful meaningful way
to me and what it means to be I guess a
human that's kind of and we say in
accordance with nature it's no zone but
someone that really kind of responds
skillfully to situations to to be a
better person and whatever that means so
I guess that's kind of like a
long-winded way to say that
stoicism to me really is an approach to
life and how to deal with the various
things that arise whether Pleasant or
unpleasant so to speak is a personal
philosophy so it begins with you and
ideally if everybody started practicing
so it is more a similar philosophy this
is not the only answer I mean there are
there are others out there you know
since the point is to become a better
person hey if everybody were to become a
better person I think there'll be a very
good beginning to were a better a better
world that said some stoic ideas have
direct social consequences one of the
fundamental stoic ideas is
cosmopolitanism the notion that we all
brothers and sisters just by virtue of
being members of the human race which
means that we should be far more
tolerant about you know foreigners and
involve international relations than we
tend to be so so those are actually
direct political implications of a stoic
outlook
stoicism to me is about choice like a
lot of times we go through our lives
kind of reacting to things and I was
really attracted to sources and because
it gave me kind of a framework in which
I could be better at making choices that
are in line with my values and being a
good person I really that's a really
important to me and you can't do that if
you're reacting to things over time it
is a way of having more agency over my
life and being able to recognize what I
can and cannot control in my life and
being able to focus on being connected
to who I really am my deeper wishes and
a practice where I can not get off track
and sort of stay connected to what
really matters to me and what I think is
correct and what actions are the best to
do and control my thoughts and
acknowledge my emotion so it's it's a
lot about mindfulness snow isn't for me
is really it's a philosophy of life it's
just a way to live my life
she says it's a set of sort of values
and principles that guide my decisions
and my actions historically stoicism is
an ancient Greek philosophy which is
concerned about living the best life you
can live there's that aspect of it
there's the theoretical aspect but for
me primarily it's a means by which to
live my life a set of tools that I used
to navigate difficult situations and a
set of arguments about what I should
value that's primarily it is it tells me
how I should conduct myself and it gives
me a set of criteria to help me make
difficult decisions primarily that being
that I should focus on being the best
person I can be
as opposed to achieving certain external
events focus on cultivating myself and
my own virtue instead of developing
wealth or something like this
it's changed my life it doesn't get more
meaningful than that it's taken time and
it's of course I'm still working on it
but when I approach dosas for the first
time it really merely resonated with me
particularly Epictetus so I I took it
seriously from the beginning I didn't
take it as just let me read this thing
it might be interesting I merely
perceived that this was potentially game
changer and it turns out I was right
I've become far more calm about a lot of
situations you know I don't get angry
that often I seem to be able to deal
with stressful occurrences much better
and I just have a more positive outlook
about things because I tend to focus on
the things around in my control and try
to train myself to accept everything
else as it comes it's definitely helped
me to to recognize when I'm feeling
overwhelmed with with something that's
happening in my life and with my
emotions and it's helped me to
dissociate from that in a healthy way so
that I can think straight and make the
decisions about how to proceed it's
helped me to understand acceptance and
and what I have to accept because I
don't have control over and what I do
have control over it's really helped me
to hone in on that and to improve my own
reactions to things which ultimately has
given me more peace in my life
throughout my life I've really been
looking for meaning in so many different
places and I you know I dabbled in
religion a little bit Buddhism but
nothing ever truly resonated with me and
I
as soon as I came across stoicism it
just immediately resonated with me and I
was able to apply it to my life and I've
actually been able to notice some real
difference in applying it when I was in
high school I mean I've always been kind
of a deep thinker
and I came across the quote the
unexamined life is not worth living and
I remember that being one of my favorite
quotes as a kid and I had absolutely no
idea that it was based in stoicism until
probably two months ago so I thought
that was pretty cool
so what kind of person would find
some useful in their lives someone who
recognizes that the world is a very
complex and uncertain place but still
wants to be effective in it I think it
really gives people a sense of a meaning
and really like core tools that they can
use in their life and personally I'm
interested in psychiatry and I'm
currently a medical student so I was
drawing a lot of parallels myself
between like mental illness like anxiety
and depression and how a lot of these
things that Stokes have been talking
about for thousands thousand years like
make up such a core part of
psychotherapy we use so like CBT rebt
like a whole bunch of basically
therapies like go on this core principle
of like what do I really control in my
life and so that's really like the big
take home for me has been how exciting
stoicism is right now and how much it's
needed especially in today's day and age
I think it's really interesting the the
relationship between cognitive
behavioral therapy and stoicism I've
read a lot of books on cognitive
behavioral therapy in the past and I
never really knew the connection but
once I actually found out that
connection it sort of sent me down a new
path of learning stoicism and it
resonated with me way more than CBT did
so I think it's it's really I think
that's really applicable to treating
mental health issues or anxiety issues
for me personally I've dealt with
anxiety my whole life and stoicism has
been the first thing that I could
actually apply to my life and I've
actually seen
you know everyone has the experience of
getting stuck in traffic or getting
stuck on the TTC you know and
no one likes it everyone grumbles I'm
actually surprised that people who kind
of you know kind of deal with it in a
very a good way and I noticed that when
that happens to me now instead of
flaring up I kind of use that as an
opportunity to exercise services and
kind of maybe do something else maybe
interact with someone next to me and I
felt like that's a that's like I needed
break in my kind of everyday kind of
grind and just it's like a instigator to
do something different at that time I
think that's really cool your story got
you to be tested every day no matter
what the occurrence is from the minor
irritations of day-to-day life to the to
the big deals right the biggest deal of
the mob probably is death right we all
face death and Seneca famously said that
death is going to be the ultimate test
of your character are you gonna be able
you know how how are you going to
approach it how are you gonna behave
when that moment comes in between you
know the mundane everyday irritations
and the ultimate test of your character
there are some other major challenges
right so one of my major challenges is
to become a better teacher and you treat
my students better in a way that it's
good for them in a way that allows them
to grow and and not in a way that would
please me because that's not the point
sometimes that's difficult because
teachers are trained to think that they
know best and then unless the students
sort of lined up with that ideal the
students not doing well but it turns out
there are many different ways of doing
well and so coming to my job with a more
open-minded attitude and a little more
tolerant attitude so what are the people
think and how they behave it's a
challenge but it's a good one social
challenges that people face that they
can apply stoicism to dealing with peer
review so people have to do with
criticism and their work for example and
maybe partly because a modern culture
you know it seems like people have lost
some of the social skills like because
they spend more time with social media I
think
and stoicism helps people to kind of
develop social skills ways of coping
with criticisms learning not to be
swayed too much by praise learning not
to be hot or offended too much by
criticism and generally coping with
workplace situations and dealing with
stress more effectively but stoicism
also provides general purpose emotional
resilience strategies that can help
people deal with difficult health
situations like undergoing surgery cope
with old age dealing with relationship
breakups any type of situation really
that could potentially be stressful
stoicism can offer people our way of
navigating
I actually there's a bear
need for it in youth today so especially
I talk about toughness about my friends
a lot I used to be a camp counselor
needs to work directly with youth in
like so much of their lives now revolve
around Instagram and what's really out
of their control so whether people are
gonna like their photos what people are
gonna comment what they think and I
think especially in some adolescents
work I've done mental illness wise
there's such a big kind of weight that I
would almost describe of like what do
people think of me are they gonna judge
me and I really think that if we can
start to teach youth these coping skills
and these skills of how to be resilient
how to understand what people think of
you and whether or not you have control
over that and what you can do for
yourself I actually think there's like a
big help that it would have on a lot of
the mental illness we say in use today
I've met natural stores you know if it
were just natural historic but even
people who don't have that natural
ability they probably need it the most
so people who are finance themselves
apologizing to people every week not
being able to control the behavior
I think that's those type of people
probably needed the most and I I would
consider myself having been one of them
so I definitely recommend it to people I
see that can't control their responses
there's a gap between the stimulus and
your response to the stimulus the world
there's lots of things happening in the
world awesome phenomena happening and
your response to it is not does not have
to be predetermined you can
in that between the stimulus and the
response and choose your response and I
think that that's a really powerful idea
we don't get taught that in school
really but it's it's huge for being a
good person I'm just developing has
became and I think is really important
we are all connected with all human
beings all creatures are connected and
adversity happens to us all and joy
happens and I think he refers to life's
wonderful web and texture which is a
great way to say it's not always roses
it's it's just it's beautiful in its
adversity and it's and it's happy times
so that I wish I could remember the
exact quote but that word that phrase
the wonderful web of life web and
texture of life
well stoic on and stoic on axis a global
movement so I think it's going to
continue growing and continue getting
bigger throughout the years and for my
part in stoic on Toronto our stoic on X
Toronto yearly we're gonna host events
and hopefully they have a great turnout
and a great vibe like this one happened
well I see stoic on access is an
important part of the international
growth of the tourism in general the
stoic movement in general because the
the major story con is great it's a lot
of fun but it's only one day once a year
and you know because of logistics only a
few hundred people cannot can actually
attend so to have these historic on axis
all over the world potentially in dozens
and dozens of different cities that
actually reaches a much larger audience
it makes the whole thing much more
flexible you can organize stoical on
axis around practices or around
discussions or about theories or about
you know local maybe faculty from
universities that that are interested in
ancient philosophy there's all sorts of
ways of doing it so stoic on axis is
vital I think for the International
growth of the stoic movement a lot of
positive feedback from this conference
like I haven't been to many conferences
but from what I've heard from people
talking so far it's definitely a
successful world and I'm just impressed
that people were so they came out you
know going to put money into it and
engage with people just like talk and
discuss these ideas and one thing I
really got out of it and said you know
if you if you passionate about something
you will find other people who are
passionate about that thing to you
and chances are you will and it's always
beautiful to engage with them it's
always worth it to try at least and it
was success so I'm happy again I think
developing community is really important
I think you know you might find yourself
being passionate about something but
you're kind of stuck in your own world
and people around you're not willing to
engage with you in that topic and I feel
like you can just you can find people
that are passionate about the same
things you're passionate about them fine
and create those communities and make
the effort if what inspiration doesn't
work try again try something else and
I'm really grateful that Peter and the
other organizers were able to put
something like this together
I think silicon X is absolutely gonna
grow this is one of the best conferences
I've been to and what unifies it is that
people are a bunch of you who are really
interested in this topic but perhaps
have been engaging on their own they've
been reading books they've been
listening to lectures perhaps that's
very private and it changes when you
enter a community when you enter a
community of people bounce ideas off of
you have people to relate to people to
help you with their own experience on
that is that is hugely beneficial for
your own practice and it's um it's it's
a really rewarding experience to see how
other people are actually into this
other people are benefiting from this
too and and I can learn from them so
this this idea of taking the theory out
of the classroom or out of the study and
taking philosophy into your life it's
huge and stoicism that's what you've
seen in still contacts you've seen what
we want we want to motivate people to
get out and talk about it and relate to
each other and hopefully build
connections that they can then network
and do something from that and that's
the value is there as long as the value
is there it's going to continue to grow
I think Stuart connects we do it in
several different cities around the
world each year and I think increasingly
what's going to happen is that when
we've had a successful school context or
maybe the means to a con conference in a
city it kind of seeds something and
there seems to be increasingly an
opportunity to have a regular annual
so here we have the meetup group that
meets every month or so and I think
we're getting to the point where we can
install clinics in Toronto as a regular
annual thing and then maybe the main
store corn conference would come back
here you know every five ten years or
something as well I think because it
seems like the audience is just growing
year on year and Toronto in particular
is one of the areas where the for
whatever reason those are a lot of
interest maybe even less may even be the
city where there's more interest than
anybody else in sources in Toronto New
York are probably the two main cities
where students become a hot subject
it's definitely a movement it's
definitely something that is a lot of
rubber popular than it was a couple
decades ago and it might just keep going
who knows but we know that you know
anxieties as all-time high possibly I
don't know according to for it a lot of
people and I think that's just going to
attract more people to kind of engage
this tourism it's not a movement in the
sense that that it is a political
movement for instance because Stoics
your people come to stoicism from all
sorts of political backgrounds you can
be a conservative libertarian and
progressive and still practice as a
stoic stoic and and benefit from it but
it is a moment in the sense that it is a
concerted effort to revitalize the
philosophy I mean there are leaders in
the movement down Robertson is the guy
that one of the people that actually
study this whole thing over several
years ago in London there are the people
that organize the stoic on in stoic week
and the various local stoic own axis so
in that sense there are organizations
there is something like my friend Greg
Lopez started recently called the stoic
fellowship which is an international
organization that fosters the
development of local stores so in that
sense is very much an organized movement
of course there is no membership cards
like you go around with a card that says
hey I'm a stoical there are no
membership fees usually either but there
is an effort by a number of people a
growing number of people to spread the
word because it's a good philosophy it's
helpful to people and if poor people
heard of it and started practicing it
you know there'll be to their benefit I
think part of the reason for this is
that people like this idea that they're
accountable and they're responsible for
the quality of their own life in some
ways that's a scary concept but in other
ways very empowering because it means
that the quality of your life is not up
to luck
it's up to the decisions you make and
the way you deal with what happens to
you so as a movement I think people are
looking for someone to tell them that
hey you can improve your lot you can you
can fix him and help your circumstance
or at least the way you react to those
that's within your grasp and here's a
set of tools on how to do
some people are naturally latching onto
that and benefiting from it I think it
is a movement I first got into it
in 2014 when Massimo penuche was
speaking on CBC radio a program that I
listened to and at that time there were
not a lot of people into it it was
really just an ancient philosophy that
academics studied and it seems to be
really really picking up in terms of
practical use and practice of it so I
think I think it's becoming a movement I
think it's really excited
I'm sure the reason why I came across
stoicism was because it is becoming more
of a movement because I think it's an
Asian philosophy but it's it's very
applicable to modern life
the stoicism is something that at first
might seem a little bit intimidating to
people because it's all these ancient
texts it's easy to see these statues of
like Greek philosophers and you're like
I don't know about that but really when
you kind of look at it it's actually
something that I think supersedes all
religion and all kinds of different
schools of thought because it really is
just a central principle and it's almost
just a way of life so I think I know
when I first read it I was kind of
scared I'm like a bit of a science guy
of in medicine I don't really know how
much I can buy with this philosophy that
I always avoided but really once you
start to dig into it it's really just
like a way to deal with life and a way
to explore what it means to be human and
what it means to live a good life
whatever that means
stoicism 101 you have a limited amount
of attention you have a limited amount
of energy that's a psychological
biological fact so the question is not
even necessarily you know what is what
can I focus on what what deserves to be
focused on what is the most effective
way to spend your focus and stoicism
tells you and this has been used by
military by athletes by by people for
generations the most effective way to
spend your focus is by orienting it
towards what you have control over and
what is up to you and by doing that
you're just in a better position to deal
with the chaos the chaos perhaps does
not go away at least not the start but
you are you are stacking the cards in
your favor and you're taking the tools
you already have and you're using them
more effectively and that's something
anybody can take just from a 5 minute 10
minute introduction of stoicism
there are common misconceptions about
store says on the you know are worth
mentioning and addressing one of them is
that people think Stoics are unemotional
they confuse it with having a stuff up a
lot because the word stoicism has come
to mean being tough minded and
unemotional but usually we spell it with
a lowercase s when we mean that when we
write capital s stores doesn't we're
talking about the ancient Greek school
of philosophy which has a much more
nuanced approach to our emotions and
it's actually the inspiration for modern
cognitive behavioral psychotherapy which
is a a very effective way of helping
people to cope with their emotions so
stoicism is more about replacing
negative emotions with healthy positive
ones and also learning to Rado and
accept certain involuntary emotional
responses so it's a slightly more
nuanced approach to managing our
emotions then then the kind of step up
all that approach and I think that's an
important message intention to address
most people understand that they tend to
be much more sympathetic these forces
are much more interested in it and like
I say know there are many more articles
and books appearing in the subject that
serve as really good introductions to
the lay reader I recommend people check
out the primary text so Marcus Aurelius
is meditations check out the letters
from Seneca and the handbook from
epictetus that is the best place to
start with the core the big three the
Roman Stoics and there's a slew of
modern stoic authors including Massimo
and Gucci and Donna Robinson that give
an excellent introduction on stone
I was at the snow upon here in Toronto
two years ago there were few hundred
people
I could see it getting a lot bigger just
because you know social media people are
sharing things like this it's very it's
very in line with Buddhism which has
been really really popular over the last
couple of decades and it's sort of a
people call it a Western a new version
of Buddhism so I think it's very
appealing to a lot of people it's it's
not it's a philosophy it's not it's not
a way of life that involves rules and
sacrifice it's not a religion it's it's
really just an empowering philosophy
that is fairly easy to understand and I
think it's probably going to pick up
so for anybody who's interested
partnering with sauces in Toronto feel
free to reach out we're a growing
community
we're the largest stoic community in the
world and we're just only gonna get
bigger and better from here on out